Inventory of the Russian pictorial collection
Hoover Institution Archives
Russian pictorial collection
1887-2005
XX764
Hoover Institution Archives
20 manuscript boxes, 3 oversize boxes, 2 boxes of glass plates, 5 boxes of slides, 10 album boxes, 96 envelopes (27.0 linear feet)
Photographs, postcards, glass plates, and slides, depicting industrial, economic, cultural, religious, and military scenes in imperial Russia and the Soviet Union, scenes of daily life, scenes from notable historical events, especially the Russian Revolution, and prominent personalities from the tsarist and Soviet periods. Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Access
The collection is open for research. Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Industries--Soviet Union.; Soviet Union--Economic conditions.; Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921.; Soviet Union--Pictorial works.
- 126 prints and postcards of the Romanov family, Imperial Russian nobility, military officers, and statesmen. (File A)
- 62 prints and postcards depicting Russian churches, icons, and other religious subjects. (File B)
- 63 prints and postcards depicting various scenes in Russia, Russian art, etc. (File C)
- 11 prints depicting the Russian Orthodox Church in Belgrade, Yugoslavia, with members of the clergy and parish. (File D)
- 8 prints depicting Tsar Nicholas II, Grand Dukes Mikhail Aleksandrovich and Sergei Aleksandrovich, Russian Imperial military officers, and a water color portrait of Napolean. (File mE)
- 2 prints of the 2nd Artillery Brigade, Feb 3, 1914, and Commanders of the Artillery Household Corps, 1900. (File m*F)
- 100 postcards depicting works of art, museum pieces, paintings, buildings, cities and scenes of daily life in Tsarist Russia. (File G)
- 87 postcards depicting works of art, museum pieces, paintings, buildings, cities and scenes of daily life in Tsarist Russia. (File H)
- 57 prints, distributed by the Soviet Government, 1950, depicting social conditions in the Soviet Union. (File mI)
- 1 print of officers of the Eesti Soomusrongide Diviisi Juhtkord (Estonian Armored Trains Division) taken during the Russian Revolution. (File mJ)
- 1 print of members of the Russian socialist organization Svobodnoge Slovo, taken at a banquet in honor of Leo E. Deutsch, New York City, 1915. (File mK)
- 1 album containing 50 prints depicting scenes in rural Russia, ca. 1900, and miscellaneous prints, postcards and magazine illustrations. (File fL)
- Glass slides of scenes in Tsarist Russia, including places of exile in Siberia, as well as of activities of the Cheka in Kiev during the civil war. (Box 1)
- 2 postcards of the Ural Mountains and 1 postcard of Serdobol (Sortavala, Finland). (File M)
- 1 print of a painting by F. Alexeev depicting a view of the Winter Palace and the Peter and Paul Fortress in St Petersburg. Original in the Tretiakov State Gallery, Moscow. (File mN)
- 1 print of a painting depicting a Russian Imperial officer of the 11th Hussar Regiment in 1839. (File O)
- 2 prints of Lt. General Chichagoff (File mP)
- 1 print of Ivan Goremykin (File Q)
- 1 print of N.I. Grigorovich (File R)
- 1 print of Aleksandr I. Guchkov (File S)
- 1 print of Vladimir N. Kokovtsov (File T)
- 1 print of Alexander Krivoshein (File U)
- 2 prints of pavel N. Miliukov (File V)
- 2 prints of Mikhail V. Rodzianko (File W)
  Scope and Contents note
  (1 is a dupilicate of the other).
- 1 print of Sergei V. Rukhlov (File X)
- 2 prints of Sergei D. Sazanov (File Y)
  (1 a duplicate of the other)
- 1 print of Andrei I. Singarev (File Z)
- 2 prints of Petr A. Stolypin (File AA)
- 1 print of Vladimir Sukhomlinov (File AB)
- 1 print of General Alexander A. Gairngrass, Chief of the Railway Guards of the Chinese Eastern Railway, 1901. (File mAC)
- 1 print depicting a group of Russian chemists at the Mendeleev Congress in St. Petersburg, 1911. (File AD)
- 1 print of Viacheslav Plehve (File AE)
- 1 print of Serge Witte (File AF)
- 2 prints of Gregori Rasputin (File AG)
  (1 is autographed)
- 1 print of Princess Irina Aleksandrovna with Prince Felix F. Yusupov (File AH)
- 2 prints of Alexandra Fydorovna, Empress of Russia (File AI)
  (1 is a duplicate of the other).
- 1 print of Nicholas II, Emperor of Russia, 1868-1918. (File AJ)
- 1 print of Nicholas II, and Grand Dukle Heritier (File mAK)
- 4 prints (and negatives) depicting Imperial Russian and Imperial Japanese officers during negotiations for settling new boundaries on Sakhalin island; 1 print (and negative) of the Russian Embassy staff in Tokyo. P. Voskevich appears in 2 prints. (File AL)
- 1 print of a poster depicting activities in the Russian Revolution of 1905. (File AM)
- 1 print depicting the Duma in session, ca. 1915-1916. (File AN)
- 83 prints, issued by the Russian Provisional Government, depicting scenes of the Russian revolution and beginning of the civil war, 1917. (File AO)
- 32 prints depicting various scenes and events of the Russian Revolution, 1917. (File AP)
- 9 prints relating to Vladimir Ipatieff: 6 prints depicting him (one with his wife), 1 print of his mother Anna, 1 print of the model of his bomb, and 1 print of his brother's house at Ekaterinburg where Tsar Nicholas II and his family were murdered. Dates, 1870-1939. (File AQ)
- 1 print of a group shot of the Maritime Regional People's Assembly (Provisional People's Assembly of the Far East). (File AR)
- 1 print depicting prominent representatives of various Allied commissions to Siberia, ca. 1918-1920. (File AT)
- 1 print of the International Military Police in Siberia, ca. 1919. (File M*AU)
- 1 album containing 32 prints taken by Henry T. Conserva, who served on board the USAT Mount Vernon, which evacuated Czech soldiers from Siberia, 1919. (File fAV)
- 9 prints depicting the atrocities committed by the Chrezvychainaia Komissiia po Bor'be s Kontry-Revoliutsiei I Sabotazhem against the White Russian forces in Kiev, ca. 1920. (File AW)
- 4 prints of the Wrangel Russian (White) Army forces concentrated on the peninsula of Gallipoli, ca. 1921. (File AX)
- 5 prints of Russian-Germans in Russia during the famine of 1922-1923. (File AY)
- 1 print of N.I. Podvoiskii and Tibor Szamuely, 1919 May (File AZ)
- 11 prints of Lev Trotskii and his wife in Mexico. (File BA)
- 2 negatives of posters from the 1930's (File BB)
- 21 prints depicting the construction of the Dnieprostroi water power plant and its opening on October 10, 1932. (File BC)
- 17 prints of the Kramatorsk Machine Tool Factory, in Kramatorsk. (File BD)
- 1 print of depicting members of the Politbureau (File BE)
- 2 prints of Viacheslav M. Molotov, 1945 (File BF)
- 2 prints of Grigorii Fedorovich Fedorov (1891- ), Soviet Government official. (File BG)
- 35 prints of the ten-day festival of Turkmenian literature and art in Moscow, October 14-23, 1955. (File mBH)
  Includes opera, dramatic performances, and concerts of musical and dance ensembles.
- 44 prints of men and women receiving the Order of Lenin, the Stalin Prize, and the Hero of Socialist Labor Award. (File mBI)
- 42 prints of the theater in Moscow, 1956, including prints of plays. (File BJ)
- 24 prints of Palaces of Culture and People's Universities in the Soviet Union, 1962. (File BK)
- 28 prints of geologists looking for oil and other minerals throughout the Soviet Union. (File BL)
- 21 prints of political leaders going through industrial plants, including prints of Nikita Khrushchev. (File mBM)
- 28 prints of cultural events such as ballet, operas, art exhibits, dramatic performances, and sporting events. (File BN)
- 22 prints depicting the life and work of the Dombas miners, 1950. (File m*BO)
- 98 prints depicting conditions in post-war Russia, intended to glorify the various achievements of Stalin and the Soviet system in general, in the fields of medicine, agriculture, industry, etc.., ca. 1945-1950. (File BP-BQ, mBR)
  Printed slogans included.
- 16 prints of scenes in Latvian S.S.R., 1950, including prints of J. Peive, President of the Latvian Academy of Sciences; Vilis Lacis, author; Andrejs Upits, author; and Anna Sakse, author. (File BS)
- 3 prints of the Russian opera singers M. Reisen, A. Pirogov, E. Gribova, and N.V. Salina. (File BT)
- 20 prints of the meeting marking the 30th anniversary of the death of American naturalist Luther Burbank, held on April 11, 1956, at the USSR society for cultural Relations with Foreign Countries. (File BU)
  Includes a print of Richard H. Davis, 2nd secretary at the U.S. Embassy in Moscow (10 prints are duplicates of the others).
- 1 scrapbook entitled Twice Hero of the Soviet Union, containing 30 prints depicting 13 men decorated for their heroism during World War II, and describing their merits 20 prints depicting Soviet life before and after World War II. (File fBV)
- ca. 150 prints relating to the Soviet military. (File fBW)
- ca. 300 prints mounted on 27 sheets, depicting life in the Soviet Union during World War II. (File fBX)
- 75 prints depicting Soviet life before and after World War II. (File fBY)
- 120 prints depicting Soviet life before and after World War II (File fBZ)
- 1 scrapbook entitled Stalingrad, containing 40 prints (Box 31)
  Formerly located in album fCA.
- 45 prints relating to Soviet arts (Album fCA)
- 1 scrapbook entitled The Restoration of Soviet Cities, 1945 containing 50 prints (Box 32)
  Formerley located in Box 32.
- 22 prints mounted on 3 cardboard matting boards relating mainly to Soviet industry and agriculture (Map case)
- 1 print of a painting by Serov of a meeting of the State Council (Gosudarstvennyi Sovet) presided by the Emperor Nicholas II. (File m*CB)
- 1 print depicting the building where the 6th congress of the Third International was held, Moscow, July 1928. (File mCC)
- 3 prints depicting Leonid Brezhnev, Konstantin Chernenko and Iurii Andropov (File CD)
- 7 prints, n.d., depicting Czech children at school in the Czech colony of Alexcandovka. (File CE)
- 91 slides depicting title pages of books in the Russian Art Collection at the Hoover Institution Library. (Box 3-7, Envelope 1-2, containing slide box 3-5, 6-7)
- 10 prints and postcards depicting the pretender to the throne Vladimir Kirilovich and his family, taken in the 1950's, and Romanov coat of arms. (File CF)
- 146 posters, 1969-1987, depicting Lenin and the Revolution; 62 posters, 1967-1969, depicting political, economic, and social conditions in the Soviet Union since the Revolution. (Box 8)
- 141 prints depicting scenes of daily life in the Soviet Union during World War II, as well as military operations and parades, buildings, public works, and political figures, including Joseph Stalin and Vyacheslav M. Molotov. (File CG-CL)
- 5 prints depicting American Red Cross ambulances and buses in Vladivostok, Siberia, ca. 1919. (File CM)
- 9 prints of churches and other buildings in Moscow, Ostankino, and Nizhnii Novgorod, 1889. (File CN)
- 40 prints of street scenes in Moscow during the August coup, 1991. (File CT)
- 5 prints of bodies of victims of demonstrations in Baku, January 1990. (File CU)
- 11 prints of scenes of demonstrations in Baku, January 1990. (File mCV)
- 58 glass plate negatives and 1 film negative of individuals, groups, events, and buildings in Russia, February-October 1917. (Box 2)
- 4 prints of atrocities against Armenians, April-May 1991. (File CW)
- 4 prints of the opening of former Estonian President Konstantin pats' grave. 1989, and examination of his skull, 1990. (File DM)
- 2 prints of Leonid and Anna Andreev, ca. 1908. (File DN)
- 1 print of V.I. Lenin, August 1923. (File DO)
- 3 prints of scenes at Red Square, Moscow, and 2 prints of political placards in Kiev, on May Day 1993. (File DP)
- 23 prints of socialists and political leaders of the Soviet Union, 1918-1923. (File DQ)
- 7 albums of prints of operations of the Russian Imperial Kirasir Household Troops Regiment and of its veterans in emigration, 1904-1974. (File fDR-DS)
- 10 prints of Soviet exploration activities in outer space, 1984-1990. (File DT)
- 6 prints of Soviet leaders, including Anatolii Lunacharskii, Karl Radek, Leon Trotsky, Joseph Stalin, Sergei Kirov, Nikita Khrushchev, Nikolai Podgornyi, Leonid Brezhnev, and Aleksei Kosygin, 1919-1965. (File DU)
- 131 postcards of buildings and miscellaneous scenes in Moscow and elsewhere in the Soviet Union, and of reproductions of Russian paintings (File DV)
- Oversize prints of Soviet cosmonauts and scenes related to Soviet space exploration. (Box 9)
- Prints of scenes of Soviet industrial production and other economic activities, 1930-1940 (Box 10-22)
- Prints of scenes of Soviet industrial production and other economic activities, 1930-1940. (Box 23-25)
- Prints, and some negatives, of scenes of Soviet Industrial production and other economic activities, and of Soviet armed forces, 1930-1940. (Box 26)
- prints of prominent Soviet political, military and other leaders, 1930-1940. (Box 27)
- Oversize caricatures of Mikhail Gorbachev and Boris Yeltsin, 1991. (Box 28)
- Prints of Joseph Stalin. (Box 29)